The Lives of the Prophets Part 1;
اَلْحَمْدُ لله ، وَالصَّلَاةُ وَالسَّلَامُ عَلى سَيِّدِنَا محمد وَعَلَى اَلِهِ وَصَحْبِهِ وَسَلِّمْ
And then he told his son;
وَكَذٰلِكَ يَجتَبيكَ رَبُّكَ وَيُعَلِّمُكَ مِن تَأويلِ الأَحاديثِ وَيُتِمُّ نِعمَتَهُ عَلَيكَ وَعَلىٰ آلِ يَعقوبَ
وَيُتِمُّ نِعمَتَهُ عَلَيكَ وَعَلىٰ آلِ يَعقوبَ كَما أَتَمَّها عَلىٰ أَبَوَيكَ مِن قَبلُ إِبراهيمَ وَإِسحاقَ ۚ
إِنَّ رَبَّكَ عَليمٌ حَكيمٌ۝
And all of these things he's deriving from this dream.
Thus will your Lord choose you,
Allah will choose you and teach you the interpretation of dreams and other things.
Taweel Al- Ahadith(تَأويل احاديث);
Taweel(تأويل) is interpretation,
Ahadith(احاديث) are speeches, words, dreams, different things.
So it doesn't necessarily mean only dreams.
It means that Allahسُبحانه وتعالى will give you wisdom to interpret things to have a good judgment
and He will perfect his favor on you and on the offspring of Yaqoob(يعقوب)
as he perfected it on your father's Ibrahim(اِبْراهِيْم) and Is'haq(إسحاق) afore time.
Verily your Lord is all Knowing all Wise.
Some men came to Rasool Allah ﷺ, and they told him;
من أكرم الناس
Who is the most noble of men.
Rasool Allah ﷺ said;
يوسُف الْكَرِيمُ ابنُ الكَرِيمِ ابْنِ الكَرِيمِ ابْنِ الكَرِيمِ
It is Yusuf(يوسُف) the Noble, the son of the Noble, the son of the Noble, the son of the Noble.
If you're asking me about the best lineage, it is Yusuf(يوسُف) the father of Yusuf(يوسُف) is a prophet.
His grandfather is a Prophet and his great grandfather is a prophet and he is a prophet himself.
That's the best lineage if you want to look at it this way,
يُوسُفُ إبنُ يَعْقُوبَ إبنِ إسْحاقَ إبنِ إبْراهِيمَ، عليهمُ السَّلاَمُ
It's an honor from Allahسُبحانه وتعالى to be a prophet
and your father is a prophet and your grandfather is a prophet and your great grandfather is a prophet.
Wherever you look up, you find the guidance of Allahسُبحانه وتعالى, an honor from Allah.
Allahسُبحانه وتعالى is telling us.
لَقَد كانَ في يوسُفَ وَإِخوَتِهِ آياتٌ لِلسّائِلينَ۝
Verily in Yusuf(يوسُف) and his brethren, there were for Ayaat(آيات) for those, who ask.
If you look at the story of Yusuf(يوسُف) and you think about it,
you would find in it, an ocean of meanings and lessons that will assist you in your life.
The brothers of Yusuf(يوسُف) knew that their father loved him more than them.
10 of them were from Different mother or mothers,
and Yusuf(يوسُف) and Binyamin(بنيامين) were from another wife of Sayedina Yaqoob(سيدنا يعقوب).
Yusuf(يوسُف) was the most beloved in the eyes of his father.
And these brothers dislike that, and they were jealous.
And we said that jealousy blinds the heart.
They said;
إِنَّ أَبانا لَفي ضَلالٍ مُبينٍ۝
Our Father is in plain error.
Why?
Because he loves Yusuf(يوسُف) more than us.
We are the men, we are the elders, we are the strongest, we are a group,
we are the ones who are going to help our Father in moments of need.
How can he love this Yusuf(يوسُف) and his brother who are young and alone.
I mean in those times, what protects you is your family
They didn't have laws and laws and law enforcement and police to take care of security.
You protect yourself through your family.
And that's why they used to be proud whenever they have a lot of family members,
the bigger your family member, the stronger you become.
So they said;
وَنَحنُ عُصبَةٌ
We are the men, who are strong.
How can our father love Yusuf(يوسُف) more than us and then they accuse their father of being an error, Zallal(ضَلالٍ) misguided.
And this is not the right thing to say about your father that your father misguided,
and you know that your father is a Nabi(نَبِي) of Allahسُبحانه وتعالى, this is because of jealousy.
The brothers of Yusuf(يوسُف) made a plan to kill, assassinate their brother.
Look at how jealousy made their thinking crooked.
The small issue of the love of their father to Yusuf(يوسُف), became very big in their eyes.
And the big issue of killing a human soul became very smell and insignificant.
It's all because of jealousy.
So jealousy made them see this little more love that Yaqoob(يعقوب) has to a son;
It's just a little much more love,
because he loves them all, all of them are his children,
but just because he loves Yusuf(يوسُف) of a little bit more.
They saw that as a great deal, a big thing, and it obsessed them and overwhelmed them and overtook their thinking,
but then killing a human being, is something normal and small.
Why?
Because of jealousy.
اقتُلوا يوسُفَ
kill him.
أَوِ اطرَحوهُ أَرضًا
or throw him out in a foreign land?
يَخلُ لَكُم وَجهُ أَبيكُم وَتَكونوا مِن بَعدِهِ قَومًا صالِحينَ۝
Your father would give you the favors alone, and after that you would be righteous folks.
They intended to make At-Toba(التوبة) before making the sin.
They said: We're going to kill him and then we're going to make At-Toba(التوبة).
One of them; who was the softest among them.
He said; No! Don't kill Yusuf(يوسُف); Instead, throw him in the well.
قالَ قائِلٌ مِنهُم لا تَقتُلوا يوسُفَ وَأَلقوهُ في غَيابَتِ الجُبِّ يَلتَقِطهُ بَعضُ السَّيّارَةِ إِن كُنتُم فاعِلينَ۝
One of them said: Kill not Yusuf(يوسُف) but if you must do something, throw him down to the bottom of a well,
he will be picked up by some caravan of travelers.
So they made a deal that they're gonna throw him in a well.
And then whenever somebody would come and take water from that well,
they're going to pick up Yusuf(يوسُف) and they're going to carry him with them
and we're going to get rid of him that way, let's not kill him.
So they went to the Father.
And they said: O our Father, why don't you trust us with yusuf(يوسف) we're strong men, we'll take care of him.
Let him come out and play with us.
Yaqoob(يعقوب) was so protective of his son, he would not let them go out and play with them.
He is always with him, he used to love his son so much.
They said;
قالوا يا أَبانا ما لَكَ لا تَأمَنّا عَلىٰ يوسُفَ وَإِنّا لَهُ لَناصِحونَ۝
Oh Our Father, why you not trust us with Yusuf(يوسُف), when we are indeed his well wishers.
Send him with us tomorrow, to enjoy himself and play, verily will take care of him.
قالَ إِنّي لَيَحزُنُني أَن تَذهَبوا بِهِ
He said;
Truly it saddens me that you should take him away from me.
Yaqoob عليه السّلام loves his son so much he can't even stand letting his son go out for a day.
I would feel sorrow, I would feel sad if you take away Yusuf(يوسُف) it from me.
He used to love his son so much.
One day is too much for him. He can't let go of his son for a day.
And then he said;
وَأَخافُ أَن يَأكُلَهُ الذِّئبُ وَأَنتُم عَنهُ غافِلونَ۝
I fear lest, a wolf should devour him while you are careless of him.
So they picked up this from their father and then they use it.
The father said I'm worried that a wolf would kill him.
These brothers were so much in a hurry to get rid of Yusuf(يوسُف)
they didn't even have time to perfect their plan.
So they picked up this word of their father.
They took out Yusuf(يوسُف) to go out and play.
They threw him in a well,
and then they took his clothes and they slaughtered the small goat and they poured the blood of that goat on his clothes.
And then they went back to their father crying.
And they said: Our father the wolf ate him.
He told him I'm afraid that the wolf the wolf ate him they said OK let's say that wolf ate him.
Allahسُبحانه وتعالى says;
فَلَمّا ذَهَبوا بِهِ وَأَجمَعوا أَن يَجعَلوهُ في غَيابَتِ الجُبِّ ۚ
So when they took him away, they all agreed to throw him down to the bottom of the well.
When they were throwing him in the well, Allahسُبحانه وتعالى reveal to Yusuf(يوسُف).
وَأَوحَينا إِلَيهِ لَتُنَبِّئَنَّهُم بِأَمرِهِم هٰذا وَهُم لا يَشعُرونَ۝
Allahسُبحانه وتعالى revealed to Yusuf(يوسُف)
and we inspire in him, indeed you shall one day inform them of this affair while they know you not.
Allahسُبحانه وتعالى told Yusuf(يوسُف);
One day you will tell your brothers about this event and they would not know that it is you, who's speaking to them.
Allah is telling Yusuf(يوسُف) about something but Yusuf(يوسُف) does not know the details of it,
when it will happen, it's a prophecy that Allahسُبحانه وتعالى has inspired to SadyinaYusuf(سَيِّدنا يوسُف).
وَجاءوا أَباهُم عِشاءً يَبكونَ۝
And they came to their fathers in the early part of the night weeping, they were crying.
قالوا يا أَبانا إِنّا ذَهَبنا نَستَبِقُ وَتَرَكنا يوسُفَ عِندَ مَتاعِنا فَأَكَلَهُ الذِّئبُ ۖ وَما أَنتَ بِمُؤمِنٍ لَنا وَلَو كُنّا صادِقينَ۝
They said: O our Father we went racing with one another
and left Yusuf(يوسُف) by our belongings and wolf devoured him, but you will never believe us.
Even when we speak the truth.
Once one of the Muslim judges, an old woman came to him in a case
and she was crying so much crying and crying, crying.
The judge ruled against her.
So then the friend of the judge said;
She's crying so much she must be telling the truth.
Why didn't you believe her?
He said, didn't you read the Qur'an that the brothers of Yusuf(يوسُف) came to their father at night crying?
Crying is not a sign of innocence, crying is not a sign of truth.
You could cry while you're lying.
So over here, the brothers of Yusuf(يوسُف), they came back home crying, but they are the ones who committed the crime.
Allahسُبحانه وتعالى says;
وَجاءوا عَلىٰ قَميصِهِ بِدَمٍ كَذِبٍ ۚ
قالَ بَل سَوَّلَت لَكُم أَنفُسُكُم أَمرًا ۖ فَصَبرٌ جَميلٌ ۖ
وَاللَّهُ المُستَعانُ عَلىٰ ما تَصِفونَ۝
And they brought his shirt stained with false blood.
He said, this is Yaqoob(يعقوب);
Nay! But your own selves have made up a tale.
He knew that they're lying.
So patience is most fitting, and it is Allah alone, whose help can be sought against that which you assert.
I mean, what is he going to do, is he going to kill his sons?
This is a dilemma for the Father.
Is he going to kill his sons?
So he said;
صبرٌ جميل
I will have patience
الله المستعان
and I would seek assistance from Allahسُبحانه وتعالى .
Yusuf(يوسُف) was in well.
A caravan of travelers pass by;
فَاَرسِلو واردهم
they sent somebody to go and get water for them.
So he inserted the bucket in the well and Yusuf(يوسُف) cling to the bucket.
And this man is pulling up the bucket looking forward to get some water, he finds in there a child.
He said;
يا بُشرىٰ هٰذا غُلامٌ
He was so happy.
Why?
Because this is a fortune.
In those times, slaves would get you a lot of money.
So they felt that they are going to sell this young child and it's a very good deal for them.
So they picked him up, took him with them in their caravan, and they went to Egypt and they sold him in Egypt.
They Sold him for a good price.
But Allahسُبحانه وتعالى says;
وَشَرَوهُ بِثَمَنٍ بَخسٍ دَراهِمَ مَعدودَةٍ وَكانوا فيهِ مِنَ الزّاهِدينَ۝
And they sold them for a low price.
Why?
Even though they got a good deal for Yusuf(يوسُف),
but Allahسُبحانه وتعالى is saying it's a low price because they never knew, who was in their hands.
They don't know who is the one they sold.
They don't know who this who this child will grow up to be.
And if they would have sold him with his weight in gold, that would have been a cheap price.
وَكانوا فيهِ مِنَ الزّاهِدينَ۝
And they were of those who regarded him as insignificant.
They didn’t know who he was this is Ghaib(غيب) in the eyes of Allahسُبحانه وتعالى, unseen.
وَقالَ الَّذِي اشتَراهُ مِن مِصرَ لِامرَأَتِهِ أَكرِمي مَثواهُ عَسىٰ أَن يَنفَعَنا أَو نَتَّخِذَهُ وَلَدًا ۚ
And he, the man from Egypt who bought him said to his wife;
Make his stay comfortable, maybe he will profit us or we shall adopt him as a son.
One of the Salaf(سلف), he says;
Three persons had a very, very good Farasah(فراسة).
Farasah(فراسة) is the ability to foresee an event, or to look in the future.
He said; One of them is this man in Egypt, he bought Yusuf(يوسُف)
and he said maybe one day he will benefit us, maybe this man will have a future.
The second is;
The daughter of the man in Madyan(مَدْيَن) who went to her father and said;
ٱسْتَـْٔجِرْهُ ۖ إِنَّ خَيْرَ مَنِ ٱسْتَـْٔجَرْتَ ٱلْقَوِىُّ ٱلْأَمِينُ
Hire him to work for you because the best man you could hire is a strong and trustworthy,
she was speaking about who?
Musa(موسى).
And third one is
Abu Bakr As-Siddique(أبوبكرالصديق), when he appointed me Umar Ibn Al-Khattab(عمرابن الخطاب) to be the Khalifah(خليفه).
He said: These are three man who had the best Farasah(فراسة), best vision ahead.
وَكَذٰلِكَ مَكَّنّا لِيوسُفَ فِي الأَرضِ وَلِنُعَلِّمَهُ مِن تَأويلِ الأَحاديثِ ۚ
Thus did we established Yusuf(يوسُف) in the land, that we might teach him the interpretation of events.
Yusuf عليه السّلام, went through slavery and was bought and sold and went through this difficulty in his life.
Why?
Because Allahسُبحانه وتعالى wants to establish him on Earth.
Lit-Tamkeen(لأتمكين)
Allahسُبحانه وتعالى is putting this Ummah(امة) in difficulty.
Why?
To prepare them for their establishment in the land.
Allahسُبحانه وتعالى put the Sahabah(صحابه) and Rasool Allah ﷺ in difficulty.
Why?
So that one day they will be prepared and ready for the establishment on the land.
Allahسُبحانه وتعالى put Musa(موسى) through misery and difficulty
and we're going to talk about the amazing story of Musa(موسى),
the difficulty that he went through and the struggling and the striving,
why?
So that Allahسُبحانه وتعالى will establish him.
Allahسُبحانه وتعالى says;
وَكَذٰلِكَ مَكَّنّا لِيوسُفَ فِي الأَرضِ
Thus did we establish
Allahسُبحانه وتعالى is calling this, establishment
because he got to Egypt, even though he was a slave, but that was the establishment for him in the future.
وَلِنُعَلِّمَهُ مِن تَأويلِ الأَحاديثِ ۚ
And we teach him the interpretation of events,
Yusuf(يوسُف) is living through a life experience so that he would develop knowledge and experience.
He's going through a lot.
And notice that Yusuf عليه السّلام, where is he being trained now.
He's been trained in the house of Al-Aziz(ألعزيز).
Al-Aziz(ألعزيز) is like the prime minister in modern terms,
not only the Prime Minister, but it's even stronger than that because he's also the treasurer in the same time,
the second most important post after the king.
So Allahسُبحانه وتعالى put Yusuf(يوسُف) in that environment even though he's a slave.
Allahسُبحانه وتعالى is putting him in the decision making Center.
He is close to these events to learn, to gain experience.
Just like Allahسُبحانه وتعالى has put Musa(موسى) where?
In the house of Firaun(فرعون).
وَاللَّهُ غالِبٌ عَلىٰ أَمرِهِ
And Allah has full power and control over His affairs.
The brothers of Yusuf(يوسُف) thought that they have control over affairs and they're going to get rid of him.
But as soon as they put Yusuf(يوسُف) in the well the matter is out of their hands.
Now Allahسُبحانه وتعالى is taking care of Yusuf(يوسُف) and things are going to turn around against them.
وَلٰكِنَّ أَكثَرَ النّاسِ لا يَعلَمونَ۝
But most of the men know not and among these men who knows not, are the brothers of Yusuf(يوسُف).
Yusuf(يوسُف) grew up in the house of Al-Aziz(ألعزيز).
Allahسُبحانه وتعالى says;
وَلَمّا بَلَغَ أَشُدَّهُ آتَيناهُ حُكمًا وَعِلمًا ۚ
And when he, Yusuf(يوسُف) attained his full manhood, we gave him wisdom and knowledge.
Thus we reward the doers of the good.
Hukma(حكما) and Ilmaa(علما).
Hukum(حكم) is judgment and Ilm(علم) is knowledge?
Why didn't Allahسُبحانه وتعالى say Hukum(حكم) only, or why didn't Allahسُبحانه وتعالى say Ilm(علم) only
these are two different things good judgment and knowledge, and Allah gave Yusuf(يوسُف) both.
If Allahسُبحانه وتعالى said: We have given him knowledge only.
Knowledge could mean that you memorize a lot of Qur'an, you know, a lot of Ahadith(احاديث).
But if you don't have a good processing of that information,
if you don't have good judgment, you can't really do much with it.
And we find that there are people who have a lot of knowledge with them, but they're limited in their ability to take advantage of it.
They're limited in their ability to make use of it.
Good judgment Hukmah(حكما) is the ability to judge events, the correct estimation and assessment of things.
You look at something and you have wisdom in the way you assess that event and the way you analyze it
and the way you deal with it and act upon it.
And that is a skill and knowledge is something else.
When you put these together, you get the perfect personality, good judgment and knowledge together.
And that is something Allahسُبحانه وتعالى has given the Ambiyaa(أنبِيَاء),
it is the Faham(فهم) and the understanding of the Deen(دِيْن) because Rasool Allah ﷺ says;
وربَّ حاملِ فِقهٍ إلى من هوَ أفقَهُ منهُ
Rasool Allah ﷺ talks about;
Maybe you are carrying Fiqh(فقه) you are delivering Fiqh(فقه) to somebody who understands this more than you.
An example of that Imam Abu Hanifah(إمام أبوحنيفه) was sitting in his Halaqah(حلقة) in his circle
and the way of Imam Abu Hanifah(إمام أبوحنيفه) in teaching was unique among the four Scholars;
With Abu Hanifah رضي الله عنه he used to have a council.
So he would present an issue for debate,
and they would discuss it and then they would give opinions and then he would make a final verdict.
With the other three Imam(اِمَام)s, they are the ones, who would give the verdict and everybody in front of them is a student.
When you're sitting in the Halaqah(حلقة) of Imam Malik(إمام مالك), you're a student.
You don't argue with Imam Malik(إمام مالك) you take from him.
With Imam Abu Hanifah(إمام أبوحنيفه), it was different.
He had, for example, Muhammed Ibn Al-Hassan(محمدإبن الحسن), and Abu Yusuf(أبويوسُف),
we don't call them students of Abu Hanifah(أبوحنيفه), we call them As-Sahiban(ألصاحبان);
The two friends or companions.
Even though there were students of Abu Hanifah(أبوحنيفه), but we don’t call them students
because they used to be a council with him, which he would discuss affairs with anyway.
There was one scholar of Hadith(حديث) who used to sit in this council of Imam Abu Hanifah(إمام أبوحنيفه)
he recited the Hadith(حديث) Imam Abu Hanifah(إمام أبوحنيفه) he did not know that, that Hadith(حديث), he did not have that knowledge.
A woman came and asked the scholar of Hadith(حديث) who was sitting in the meeting of Abu Hanifah(أبوحنيفه) a question;
she asked him a question;
That scholar of Hadith(حديث) said; Allah Ho Alam(الله أعلم), I don't know the answer.
Imam Abu Hanifah(إمام أبوحنيفه) said: I know the answer.
So the scholar of Hadith(حديث) said: O Imam(اِمَام) how did he know the answer?
He said: I knew the answer from the Hadith(حديث) you just recited.
So this is an example of somebody who's carrying the knowledge, but did not know how to implement it;
While Imam Abu Hanifah(إمام أبوحنيفه) did not have it, but when he had it, he knew how to use it.
Allahسُبحانه وتعالى has given Yusuf عليه السّلام, both Hukum(حكم) and Ilm(علم) good judgment on events and knowledge.
And this is something very important for anybody in a position of leadership.
It's not enough to have knowledge and it's not good only to have good judgment.
You need to have both to be an effective and successful leader.
There is an Islamic state that happened in the North Africa a few centuries ago,
this Islamic State was established by Ulema(علماء).
And they implemented the Shariah(شريعة) and it was one of the honors of the Islamic history.
When the scholars analyze the reasons of the downfall of that Islamic State,
they say one of the reasons is because these scholars lost touch with the reality of the world around them.
They had a lot of knowledge, but they lost touch with the reality of the world.
They were too much busy studying the details of Fiqh(فقه) and Tafriat Al-Faqihaa(تفريات فقيهة)
and they lost touch with the world around them and what that was one of the reasons why that state fell and was overtaken.
Even though they were establishing Shariah(شريعة) and they were scholars, there's no doubt in their righteousness.
Yuusuf عليه السّلام grew up in the house of Al-Aziz(ألعزيز).
One of the Islamic scholars gives an estimate of the age of Yusuf(يوسُف), when he was adopted.
He says he was about maybe 14 years old.
Because Ghulam(غلام) when they have taken him from the well and they said; Ghulam(غلام);
that is usually the age of a Ghulam(غلام), older than that is called Fatah(فتحى).
And he says that;
بَلَغَ أَشُدَّهُ
would mean 25 years old, even though there's a difference in opinion on what is Balagha Ashudda(بَلَغَ أَشُدَّهُ);
we can give an estimate that the wife of Al-Aziz(ألعزيز) at that time was about 40 years old.
Because if they have adopted Yusuf(يوسُف) when he was 14,
and let's say that she was maybe 30 years old, because her husband was already the Aziz(عزيز)
and usually to have a position of that status, you might be 40 years old.
So by the time Yusuf(يوسُف) grows up to be 25, she might have been at that time, 40 years old.
The wife of Al-Aziz(ألعزيز) presented herself to SadyinaYusuf(سَيِّدنا يوسُف)
and she in whose house he was sought to seduce him.
وَغَلَّقَتِ الأَبوابَ
And she closed the doors.
وَقالَت هَيتَ لَكَ ۚ
And she said: Come on you.
She tried to sleep with him by force.
She brought him into that room, close the doors, presented herself to him and wanted to force him to commit the act of Zina(زنا).
قالَ مَعاذَ اللَّهِ ۖ
He said: I seek refuge in Allah.
إِنَّهُ رَبّي أَحسَنَ مَثوايَ ۖ
Truly your husband is my master and he made my stay agreeable.
إِنَّهُ لا يُفلِحُ الظّالِمونَ۝
I will never, never betray him because the wrongdoers will never be successful.
Subhaan Allah(سُبْحَان الله).
قالَ مَعاذَ اللَّهِ ۖ
I seek refuge in Allah.
So first of all, look at this, first of all, he's not stopping her, in his confidence in his own self.
He's asking Allah to help him, Maadh Allah(معاذ); I seek refuge in Allah; O Allah help me.
And then he said;
إِنَّهُ رَبّي أَحسَنَ مَثوايَ ۖ
Your husband is my master, and he has been very well with me; he has treated me very well.
Look at the gratitude that SadyinaYusuf(سَيِّدنا يوسُف) had,
even though he was a slave, and this was a slave master, he did not have any hatred against him.
In fact, he viewed him as somebody who needs to be respected because he dealt with him in a very good and respectable way.
And then he said;
إِنَّهُ لا يُفلِحُ الظّالِمونَ۝
The ones, who betray and the ones who do wrong; they can never be successful.
Allahسُبحانه وتعالى says;
وَلَقَد هَمَّت بِهِ ۖ
وَهَمَّ بِها لَولا أَن رَأىٰ بُرهانَ رَبِّهِ ۚ
And indeed, she did desire him, and he would have inclined to her desire; Had he not seen the evidence of His Lord.
She desired him.
وَلَقَد هَمَّت بِهِ ۖ
And he had also this Hum(همَّ); Wa Hamma Biha(وهمَّ بهَا);
her desire she was acting upon it.
Her desire was in her heart, but she was acting upon it.
This idea passed through his heart, but he did not act upon it.
And we know from the Hadith(حديث) Rasool Allah ﷺ says;
If you make the intention to do evil; And then you do it,
Allahسُبحانه وتعالى will write it down against you as one evil deed.
And if you think about doing evil, but then you do not do it, Allahسُبحانه وتعالى will write it as a good deed.
So the thought itself passed through the heart of Yusuf عليه السّلام, but he did not act upon it.
And he shut that door, and he sought refuge in Allahسُبحانه وتعالى and he drove it out of his heart, and he refused.
In itself, what I'm presenting to you now,
a fact that a beautiful woman presents herself to a man that in itself is difficult.
Now let's look at the other elements and variables in this situation, that would even complicate it further.
Number one, this woman was extremely beautiful, and she was wealthy and she was his master.
So, she has the power to force him and if he does not obey her, she can punish him.
Number two,
we cannot believe that she resorted to such extreme measures suddenly in that moment.
No!
A woman will not resort to using force except if she has exhausted all other means.
She must have tried everything possible.
Before she started using force.
And imagine this because SadyinaYusuf(سَيِّدنا يوسُف) was living with her.
So SadyinaYusuf(سَيِّدنا يوسُف) it wasn't a matter; it wasn't a spur of the moment.
SadyinaYusuf(سَيِّدنا يوسُف) was going through this pain and Fitnah(فِتْنَه) for a long time.
He has been presented to the seduction for a very, very long period,
because she will not act this way, shut the doors and try to force him
except if she has tried all other means before and they didn't work.
So she must have been doing this for months or maybe even years.
This is the complication of the situation because it's difficult to stop it, even if it's a spur of the moment thing.
But it makes it even much, much more difficult to stop if you have been going through this for years.
And you are living with her in the same house seeing her there night.
And they are the one who are feeding you and taking care of you and there's interaction
and he will have sumooh(سمعو), he had persistence and he was able to stop this Fitnah(فِتْنَه)
and say I seek refuge in Allahسُبحانه وتعالى
that's is why SadyinaYusuf(سَيِّدنا يوسُف) is the leader of the ones, who come under the shade of Allahسُبحانه وتعالى in the Day of Judgment.
وَرَجُلٌ دَعَتْهُ امْرَأَةٌ ذَاتُ مَنْصِبٍ وَجَمَالٍ فَقَالَ: إِنِّي أَخَافُ اللَّهَ
A man who was called by a woman
دات حصبٍ وَجَمَالٍ
beauty, and position and he says I fear Allah.
This woman had Hasab(حصب) she had position.
She had wealth she had Mal(مال), she had beauty, she had everything.
SadyinaYusuf(سَيِّدنا يوسُف) was able to stand against this sea of seduction and stop it.
Allahسُبحانه وتعالى says;
كَذٰلِكَ لِنَصرِفَ عَنهُ السّوءَ وَالفَحشاءَ ۚ إِنَّهُ مِن عِبادِنَا المُخلَصينَ۝
We might turn away from him evil and illegal sexual intercourse.
Surely he was one of Our chosen guided slaves.
Allahسُبحانه وتعالى says that he had Ikhlas(إخلاص) and he was chosen.
She wouldn't accept that answer from him.
So she tried to force him.
He ran out of the room and open the door and try to leave.
And she grabbed him by his shirt in the back and tried to pull him back and his shirt was torn apart.
That moment, her husband walked in the room.
وَاستَبَقَا البابَ وَقَدَّت قَميصَهُ مِن دُبُرٍ وَأَلفَيا سَيِّدَها لَدَى البابِ ۚ
So they raised with one another to the door, and she tore his shirt from the back.
They both found their Lord.
Lord here mean husband,
قالَت ما جَزاءُ مَن أَرادَ بِأَهلِكَ سوءًا
Look at how she changed the story.
She said: What is the recompense for him, who intended an evil design against your wife?
What will the punishment be of a man who intended evil against your wife?
Immediately she was able to pronounce that word, reaction that was sudden and this happened in front of Yusuf عليه السّلام.
Clear lie in front of him. And then, she said;
إِلّا أَن يُسجَنَ أَو عَذابٌ أَليمٌ۝
And then gave suggestions for the punishment, not only what punishment should be given, but she gave suggestions.
What did she say?
Except that he be put in prison or a painful torment.
She did not say kill him.
Because she doesn't want him to be killed.
She said: Put him in jail or punishment him.
But she did not suggest killing him.
قالَ هِيَ راوَدَتني عَن نَفسي ۚ
Yusuf(يوسُف) said: It is she that sought to seduce me.
Now how could he solve this problem?
Yusuf(يوسُف) is saying something and the wife is say something else.
Allahسُبحانه وتعالى in that moment sent one out their relatives.
So he came and he said: I will tell you how can we tell the truth.
If the shirt of Yusuf(يوسُف) of is torn from the front, then she is telling the truth.
If the shirt of Yusuf(يوسُف) is torn from the back, then she is lying.
Because if the shirt is torn from the front,
it means that Yusuf(يوسُف) was attacking her and she was fighting him so his shirt was torn.
If the shirt is torn from the back, it means that she was running after him trying to grab him.
So it's a very wise suggestion.
His shirt was torn from the back; so she was lying.
فَلَمّا رَأىٰ قَميصَهُ قُدَّ مِن دُبُرٍ قالَ إِنَّهُ مِن كَيدِكُنَّ ۖ إِنَّ كَيدَكُنَّ عَظيمٌ۝
So when he saw his shirt torn at the back, he said;
Surely it is a plot of, you woman.
Certainly mighty is your plot.
And then the husband told you Yusuf(يوسف).
يوسُفُ أَعرِض عَن هٰذا ۚ
O Yusuf(يوسف) of turn away from this.
Meaning ignore it. Don't speak about it as if nothing happened.
Let's not cause this problem to be known to anyone.
And they don't want any of this to leak, they don't want the scandal.
It will be a political scandal for them.
So he told Yusuf(يوسُف), don't speak about it as if it never happened, cover up
and then he told his wife.
وَاستَغفِري لِذَنبِكِ ۖ إِنَّكِ كُنتِ مِنَ الخاطِئينَ۝
Ask forgiveness for your sin,
إِنَّكِ كُنتِ مِنَ الخاطِئينَ۝
Verily you were of the sinful.
We can find the sense of spoilness in this response of Al-Aziz(ألعزيز),
and this is common among the high class when they become corrupt.
He told Yusuf(يوسُف) forget about this.
And then he told his wife, can you please ask Allah to forgive you?
And that was the end of the story.
There's no real jealousy in that man, he said;
وَاستَغفِري لِذَنبِكِ ۖ
Ask Allah to forgive you.
إِنَّكِ كُنتِ مِنَ الخاطِئينَ۝
You were of those who are sinful.
But the high class society, they have a lot of spare time.
And the woman get together and they gossip.
Some woman from this particular level, the luxurious, extravagant, rich and famous of the high class,
they knew somehow of the event that happened.
And they knew that the wife of Al-Aziz(ألعزيز) has love to her slave;
so they started speaking about that.
وَقالَ نِسوَةٌ فِي المَدينَةِ امرَأَتُ العَزيزِ تُراوِدُ فَتاها عَن نَفسِهِ ۖ قَد شَغَفَها حُبًّا ۖ
And women in the city said: The wife of Al-Aziz(ألعزيز) is seeking to seduce her slave, young man.
قَد شَغَفَها حُبًّا ۖ
Indeed she loves him violently.
إِنّا لَنَراها في ضَلالٍ مُبينٍ۝
We see her in plain error.
I mean how good she desires slave
and gossip was going around and the news is spreading from one meeting and club to another.
So the wife of Al-Aziz(ألعزيز) wanted to teach them a lesson.
She invited this woman and then she gave them some fruits.
She gave them knives.
And then she told them to start eating
so they would cut the fruits with the knives and she had already prepared her slave Yusuf(يوسُف)
and Rasool Allah ﷺ says that Yusuf(يوسُف) of had one half of the beauty.
Yusuf(يوسُف), there was no one more handsome than him.
Rasool Allah ﷺ says: I saw him in As-Samah(ألسماوة),
when Rasool Allah ﷺ made the trip of Al-Miraj(ألمعراج).
Rasool Ullah said;
فَمَرَرْتُ بِيُوسُفَ وَإِذَا هُوَ قَدْ أُعْطِيَ شَطْرَ الْحُسْنِ
I saw Yusuf(يوسُف) and he had half of the beauty.
Ibn Masood(إبن مسعود) later would say that whenever Yusuf(يوسُف) would deal with any woman he would cover his face.
The interpreters of this Hadith(حديث) they say it could either mean that Yusuf(يوسُف) of had half of the beauty of the world
or it could mean that Yusuf(يوسُف) of had half of the beauty of who?
Adam(آدَم).
Adam عليه السّلام because Allahسُبحانه وتعالى has created Adam(آدَم) with his own hands
and the scholar said that was the best form of human beings.
So Yusuf(يوسُف) of had half of the beauty of Adam(آدَم).
So they started eating and she made Yusuf(يوسُف) walk in front of them.
Yusuf(يوسُف) walked in front of these women.
They were cutting these fruits and they looked up and they saw Yusuf(يوسُف) walking
and they kept on staring at Yusuf(يوسُف) and the knife is moving, until it started cutting through their flesh
and cutting their fingers
and when Yusuf(يوسُف) have passed away, they realize that they have cut their own hands.
And they said;
فَلَمّا رَأَينَهُ أَكبَرنَهُ وَقَطَّعنَ أَيدِيَهُنَّ وَقُلنَ حاشَ لِلَّهِ ما هٰذا بَشَرًا إِن هٰذا إِلّا مَلَكٌ كَريمٌ۝
Then when they saw him, they exalted him at his beauty.
And in their astonishment cut their hands.
They said: How perfect is Allah ?
No man is this; this is none other than a noble Angel.
So this cannot be a man, this is an angel.
Now they understood what the wife of Al-Aziz(ألعزيز) is going through.
So she told them;
قالَت فَذٰلِكُنَّ الَّذي لُمتُنَّني فيهِ ۖ وَلَقَد راوَدتُهُ عَن نَفسِهِ فَاستَعصَمَ ۖ
وَلَئِن لَم يَفعَل ما آمُرُهُ لَيُسجَنَنَّ وَلَيَكونًا مِنَ الصّاغِرينَ۝
She said: This is he; the young man about whom you did blame me for his love.
And I did seek to seduce him, but he refused.
And now if he refuses to obey my order, he shall certainly be cast into prison,
and he will be one of those who are disgraced.
She's still running after him and threatening him.
And the woman who saw him now we're all encouraging him to obey his master.
They were telling him, she's your master, you have to obey her.
So now the pressure is not only from the wife of Al-Aziz(ألعزيز),
but the pressure is from all these other women who saw him.
Now things are becoming very, very difficult and painful and distressful and SadyinaYusuf(سَيِّدنا يوسُف).
He's going through Fitnah(فِتْنَه) and his life is distressful.
He's living in a big prison, a prison of Fitnah(فِتْنَه);
all around him his Fitnah(فِتْنَه), seduction is surrounding him from every side.
So Yusuf(يوسف) said;
قالَ رَبِّ السِّجنُ أَحَبُّ إِلَيَّ مِمّا يَدعونَني إِلَيهِ ۖ
He said: O my lord, prison is more to my liking than that which they invite me to.
Now for Yusuf(يوسُف), living in prison is easier than living out of prison.
What he's going through out of prison outside of prison is worse.
He said: O Allah take me to jail.
At least I will be away from this Fitnah(فِتْنَه); it's better for me.
Subhaan Allah(سُبْحَان الله), Yusuf(يوسُف) is doing all of this to keep away from one of the most powerful seducing things that could affect a man.
Not only is it the beauty and the and the lust and the encouragement of the woman and the society and the environment that Yusuf(يوسُف) is living in,
but he's also being coerced and forced to commit Zina(زنا).
Yusuf(يوسُف) said: O Allah take me to jail
going to jail is better for me than responding to what they want me to do.
And then he said;
وَإِلّا تَصرِف عَنّي كَيدَهُنَّ أَصبُ إِلَيهِنَّ وَأَكُن مِنَ الجاهِلينَ۝
Unless You turn away their plot from me,
I will feel inclined towards them and be one of those who commit the sin and one of those who are ignorant.
He said: O Allah, if you do not take away this from me, I am weak;
I am weak and I'm going to fall into this.
An admission from SadyinaYusuf(سَيِّدنا يوسُف) of his weakness, we are weak.
We should never think that we're strong.
Our strength comes from Allahسُبحانه وتعالى
and this is the Dua(دُعَا) that we should say, in environments like this, which are similar to the environment of Yusuf عليه السّلام.
وَإِلّا تَصرِف عَنّي كَيدَهُنَّ أَصبُ إِلَيهِنَّ وَأَكُن مِنَ الجاهِلينَ۝
O Allah unless you turn away their plot from me; I will feel inclined towards them and be one of the ignorance.
فَاستَجابَ لَهُ رَبُّهُ فَصَرَفَ عَنهُ كَيدَهُنَّ ۚ
إِنَّهُ هُوَ السَّميعُ العَليمُ۝
So his Lord answered his invocation and turn away from him, their plot.
Verily He is the All Hearer and the All Knower.
ثُمَّ بَدا لَهُم مِن بَعدِ ما رَأَوُا الآياتِ لَيَسجُنُنَّهُ حَتّىٰ حينٍ۝
Then it appeared to them after they had seen the proofs of his innocence to imprison him for a time.
Now the news is spread; it's a scandal now.
How can they solve the problem by taking the innocent to jail.
Instead of stopping, the wife of Al-Aziz(ألعزيز) they took the Nabi(نَبِي) of Allah Yusuf(يوسُف) and they put him in jail.
He was oppressed, and put in jail even though he was innocent.
There were two men who were with him in jail.
And these two men saw a dream;
one of them saw a dream in which he is pressing wine
and the other one saw a dream in which he is carrying on his head some bread
and there are some birds who are eating from that bread.
وَدَخَلَ مَعَهُ السِّجنَ فَتَيانِ ۖ قالَ أَحَدُهُما إِنّي أَراني أَعصِرُ خَمرًا ۖ
وَقالَ الآخَرُ إِنّي أَراني أَحمِلُ فَوقَ رَأسي خُبزًا تَأكُلُ الطَّيرُ مِنهُ ۖ نَبِّئنا بِتَأويلِهِ ۖ
إِنّا نَراكَ مِنَ المُحسِنينَ۝
They said: Because we see that you are of those, who are righteous.
We want you to tell us the interpretation of this dream.
Yusuf عليه السّلام told them;
No food will come to you, but I will inform you it's interpretation before it comes.
قالَ لا يَأتيكُما طَعامٌ تُرزَقانِهِ إِلّا نَبَّأتُكُما بِتَأويلِهِ قَبلَ أَن يَأتِيَكُما ۚ
The Mufassireen(مفسرين) have different opinions about this one of them is that
Sayidina Yusuf عليه السّلام told them I will tell you the interpretation of the dream before your next meal is served.
Before your next meal is served, you will have the interpretation of the dream.
And then notice the personality of the Daiyah(داعية), the preacher to Islam.
They asked him a question about an interpretation of a dream.
He said;
ذٰلِكُما مِمّا عَلَّمَني رَبّي ۚ
Now this is number two.
Number one;
He told them.
طَعامٌ تُرزَقانِهِ
Before you receive your next meal, but he said;
Turzaqanihi(ترزقانه)
it is Rizq(رزق) from Allah.
So he's driving some concepts to them.
So number one is telling them that this food that you will receive is from Allah.
ذٰلِكُما مِمّا عَلَّمَني رَبّي ۚ
That is of the knowledge that Allahسُبحانه وتعالى has taught me.
Meaning I'm not gonna tell you the interpretation of the dream from my own knowledge and skills.
This is knowledge that Allahسُبحانه وتعالى has taught me.
So he's giving credit to Allahسُبحانه وتعالى.
Number three;
إِنّي تَرَكتُ مِلَّةَ قَومٍ لا يُؤمِنونَ بِاللَّهِ وَهُم بِالآخِرَةِ هُم كافِرونَ۝
I have abandoned the religion of a people that believe not in Allah.
Now what does this have to do with interpretation of the dreams?
This is pure Da'wah(دعوة), that he is delivering to these people.
He said: I have left the religion of the people, who disbelieve in Allah.
He is talking about the religion that they're following.
He said: I have abandoned that religion,
وَهُم بِالآخِرَةِ هُم كافِرونَ۝
And they disbelieve in the Akhirah(آخرة).
So he is establishing in them the belief in Allah and the belief in Akhirah(آخرة)
because there is no religion that was revealed to Nabi(نَبِي), except that it has in it; a pillar of faith, which is Akhirah(آخرة).
And then number five, he said;
وَاتَّبَعتُ مِلَّةَ آبائي إِبراهيمَ وَإِسحاقَ وَيَعقوبَ ۚ
And I followed the religion of my father's Ibrahim(اِبْراهِيْم), Is'haq(إسحاق) and Yaqoob(يعقوب).
Why did he tell them that I followed the religion of my fathers.
Ibrahim عليه السّلام was the caller of truth of Tawheed(توحيد) in that time.
He was the believer.
And the belief in Allahسُبحانه وتعالى was among his children, it wasn't widespread.
So the family of Ibrahim عليه السّلام were famous that they were the families of Islam.
The people in Egypt have heard about the news of Ibrahim(اِبْراهِيْم) and this Is'haq(إسحاق) and Yaqoob(يعقوب) and the religion of Tawheed(توحيد).
So Yusuf(يوسُف) is telling them about it; He's telling them this is the religion that I follow.
So he's telling them: I'm following the religion of my father's Ibrahim(اِبْراهِيْم) and Is'haq(إسحاق) and Yaqoob(يعقوب)
because they were the representations after Tawheed(توحيد).
They were the representations of the oneness of Allahسُبحانه وتعالى .
It was among this blessed family of Ibrahim عليه السلام.
Number six;
ما كانَ لَنا أَن نُشرِكَ بِاللَّهِ مِن شَيءٍ
And never could we attribute any partners whatsoever to Allah.
The people in Egypt at that time knew the concept of Allah but they knew it in a form of Shirk(شرك);
because we'll find throughout the story of Yusuf(يوسُف) that they knew about Allah;
because we talked about Al-Aziz(ألعزيز) is telling his wife;
فاستغفري لذنبك
Ask Allah to forgive your sin.
So they knew about Allahسُبحانه وتعالى but they were attributing, other gods with him like the people of Quraish(قُرَيْشْ),
they knew about Allahسُبحانه وتعالى;
But they used to believe in other idols and gods and then he said;
ذٰلِكَ مِن فَضلِ اللَّهِ عَلَينا وَعَلَى النّاسِ وَلٰكِنَّ أَكثَرَ النّاسِ لا يَشكُرونَ۝
Number seven;
this is from the grace of Allah to us and to mankind.
وَلٰكِنَّ أَكثَرَ النّاسِ لا يَشكُرونَ۝
But most of mankind do not thank.
Yusuf(يوسُف) is saying that this message of Tawheed(توحيد) is a blessing of Allah on us and it's a blessing of Allah on all mankind.
Because the Ibrahim عليه السّلام was calling everyone to Islam, so it's a blessing on everyone.
The religion of Allahسُبحانه وتعالى is a blessing for everyone.
This is an introduction and then he came to interpret the dream.
But he gave them another introduction before he interpreted the dream.
They asked him a straight question; Tell us the interpretation of this dream.
What was his answer?
He said;
يا صاحِبَيِ السِّجنِ
O companions of the prison and look at the choice of words.
O companions; he's taking them as companions and friends.
He is having a social relation with them some closeness?
يا صاحِبَيِ السِّجنِ
A very soft way of speaking to them; O companions of jail, you're my companions.
And then he sends a question to them;
يا صاحِبَيِ السِّجنِ أَأَربابٌ مُتَفَرِّقونَ خَيرٌ أَمِ اللَّهُ الواحِدُ القَهّارُ۝
Are many different gods better or Allah, the One that irresistible?
He's not telling them straightly Allah is better; He's asking them a question; to make them use their mind.
It is obvious because why is he asking this particular question?
Because it is obvious to the human intellect and the human mind and the human heart, that there's only one God.
Allah is Al-Qahhaar(ألقهار)
Al-Qahhaar(ألقهار) means He is the one, who is overwhelming and dominant over everything.
So all of these other gods that you are establishing, besides Allah, they have no power whatsoever.
So he ask them this question.
And then he's giving them the answer.
He gave them the question so that they would think,
and he's preparing them to receive the next piece of information that he will give them.
He told them;
ما تَعبُدونَ مِن دونِهِ إِلّا أَسماءً سَمَّيتُموها أَنتُم وَآباؤُكُم
سَمَّيتُموها أَنتُم وَآباؤُكُم ما أَنزَلَ اللَّهُ بِها مِن سُلطانٍ ۚ
You do not worship besides Him but only names which you have forged - you and your father's for which Allah has sent down no authority.
Asmaa(أسماء) names, what is the name?
A name is an abstract thing, the name itself has no value, the substance which are naming that has the value.
Yusuf(يوسُف) is telling them that these gods have no substance, they don't even exist.
There's nothing behind it; it's just a name; it's just a label; there's nothing behind it.
أَسماءً سَمَّيتُموها
These are names you forged with your father's before.
ما أَنزَلَ اللَّهُ بِها مِن سُلطانٍ ۚ
Allahسُبحانه وتعالى did not instruct or commanded us to do this.
Then he said;
إِنِ الحُكمُ إِلّا لِلَّهِ ۚ
The command is for none but Allah;
Al-Hukm(ألحكم); the governance and the rule and the command belongs to Allahسُبحانه وتعالى in all of our affairs in everything,
we need to realize that we are following an incomplete form of Islam today.
We're following the brand of Islam that is missing the Shariah(شريعة).
The Shariah(شريعة) is left out.
We are following a certain aspect of Islam which is the daily rituals of Ibadah(عبادة)
and some things that we do in the Masjid(مسجد) and some very little Akhlaq(أخلاق) that we have and that's it.
But we're missing the Shariah(شريعة); the law of Allahسُبحانه وتعالى
we're missing the important Akhlaq(أخلاق), we're missing the way of dealing in business, we're missing all of this.
And if we do not have the intention to bring it back, and if we do not strive and struggle to do so,
then we are guilty of following an incomplete form of Islam.
And the only excuse we would have in front of Allahسُبحانه وتعالى is;
if we strive and struggle to bring back the complete form of Islam.
If we do that, then we hope that Allahسُبحانه وتعالى will forgive us for this shortcoming.
Yusuf(يوسُف) is saying;
إِنِ الحُكمُ إِلّا لِلَّهِ ۚ
All Command belongs to Allah.
Do we follow the commandments of Allah in business?
Do we follow the commandments of Allah in criminal law.?
Do we follow the commandments of Allah in international law?
Do you follow the commandments of Allah in politics?
Do you follow the commandments of Allah in economics?
Do you follow the commandments of Allah in social laws?
If we are leaving all of this out, what are we following?
And then Yusuf(يوسُف) is telling them, the justification, why the rules should belong to Allah
because he says;
أَمَرَ أَلّا تَعبُدوا إِلّا إِيّاهُ ۚ
He has ordered you to worship none but Him; so this is part of worship.
The reason why, Hukum(حكم) should belong to Allah; is because it is part of worship.
And if we are not worshiping Allah in the laws of social life and politics and economics,
that means we are taking other gods besides Allah.
And that's why when Odae Bin Hatim(عدئ بن حاتم) walked in;
Rasool Allah ﷺ saw a cross hanging on his chest?
And Rasool Allah ﷺ said;
اتَّخَذُوا أَحْبَارَهُمْ وَرُهْبَانَهُمْ أَرْبَابًا من دون الله
They have taken their priests and the rabbi's Gods besides Allah.
Odae Bin Hatim(عدئ بن حاتم) said: No; We do not worship our priests.
He was a Christian who had the cross hanging on his chest.
Rasool Allah ﷺ said: Didn't your priests make the Halal(حلال); Haram(حرام) and the Haram(حرام); Halal(حلال)?
He said: Yes! He said that is worshipping them.
If you give a human being the authority to say that the Halal(حلال) is Haram(حرام) and the Haram(حرام) is Halal(حلال),
you have taken him as a god besides Allah.
And that is what we have done in a lot of aspects of our life.
Actually the major portion of our life, we have given the authority to man and we have taken it from Allahسُبحانه وتعالى.
So Yusuf(يوسُف) is telling them;
إِنِ الحُكمُ إِلّا لِلَّهِ ۚ أَمَرَ أَلّا تَعبُدوا إِلّا إِيّاهُ ۚ
Allahسُبحانه وتعالى the commandment belongs to Him and Allah has instructed you to worship none but Him.
ذٰلِكَ الدّينُ القَيِّمُ وَلٰكِنَّ أَكثَرَ النّاسِ لا يَعلَمونَ۝
That is the true religion; If you want the true religion that is the true religion.
وَلٰكِنَّ أَكثَرَ النّاسِ لا يَعلَمونَ۝
But most men know not.
صَلَّى الله عَلى سَيَّدِنَا محمد وَعَلى اَلِهِ وَ صَحْبِهِ وَسَلِّمْ